<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Tarlton's Jests</title>
            <principal>
               <persName xml:id="JAKA1">Diane K. Jakacki</persName>
            </principal>
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="BAZA1">Riley Bazaar</persName>
               <resp>editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="BEAR1">Haley Beardsley</persName>
               <resp>editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="BROO1">Aden Brooks</persName>
               <resp>editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="CALD1">Julia Calderone</persName>
               <resp>editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="DERR1">Luke Derr</persName>
               <resp>editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="HASF1">Andrew Hasfal</persName>
               <resp>editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="HEIN1">Rebecca Heintzelman</persName>
               <resp>editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="KIZI1">Jackson Kizilbash</persName>
               <resp>editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="KRES1">Megan Krestinski</persName>
               <resp>editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="KURU1">Viveka Kurup</persName>
               <resp>editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="KYAW1"> Wera Kyaw Kyaw</persName>
               <resp>editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="MIYA1">Tsugunobu Miyake</persName>
               <resp>editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="MUEL1">Nick Mueller</persName>
               <resp>editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="MURR1">James Murray</persName>
               <resp>editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="YIGA1">Quinton Nsamba Yiga</persName>
               <resp>editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="OLDF1">Morgan Oldfield</persName>
               <resp>editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="PAPA1">Lucas Papaleo</persName>
               <resp>editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="PURI1">Livy Puri</persName>
               <resp>editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="PYON1">Jason Pyon</persName>
               <resp>editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="ROBE1">Jack Roberto</persName>
               <resp>editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="SCHA1">Katie Schaefer</persName>
               <resp>editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="SCHM1">Caleb Schmidt</persName>
               <resp>editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="SIMS1">Sullivan Sims</persName>
               <resp>editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="SOTI1">Harrison Sotir</persName>
               <resp>editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="WARD1">Lily Ward</persName>
               <resp>editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="ZELI1">Tim Zelikovsky</persName>
               <resp>editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>HUMN100: Digging into the Digital</publisher>
            <authority>Bucknell University</authority>
            <pubPlace>Lewisburg, PA</pubPlace>
            <date when-iso="2022-10">October 2022</date>
            <availability>
               <licence>Creative Commons License - Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0
                  International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <imprint>
                     <biblScope>
                        <title type="main">Tarltons Ie∫ts.</title>
                        <title type="sub">Drawne into three parts</title>
                        <title type="section">1 His Court-wittie Ie∫ts</title>
                        <title type="section">2 His ∫ound Cittie Ie∫ts.</title>
                        <title type="section">3 His Country prettie Ie∫ts.</title>
                        <title type="sub">Full of Delight, Wit, and hone∫t Myrth.</title>
                        <figure/>
                     </biblScope>
                     <pubPlace>LONDON.</pubPlace>
                     <distributor> Printed for <persName type="publisher">Iohn Budge</persName>, and
                        are to be ∫old at his shop, at the <placeName>great South doore at
                           Paules</placeName>. <date when-custom="1613">1613</date>. </distributor>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="section" xml:id="COUR">
            <head><title>Tarlton's Court Witty Jests</title></head>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="COUR01">
               <byline resp="#BAZA1"><persName>Riley Bazaar</persName></byline>

               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>Tarlton Played the Drunkard Before the Queen</title></head>
                  <ab>The Queen was not content: Tarlton saw this and took it upon himself to make
                     her smile. To do so, he acted like a drunk and asked for beer to be brought to
                     him immediately: The Queen acknowledged and embraced his silly act and
                     commanded him to not have any more to drink, or else he would truly be a mess!
                     Tarlton responded to her and told her to not fear, due to the fact that her
                     beers are small and not impactful to him. To this, the Queen knew he was joking
                     and laughed, commanding that he should definitely not have any more! </ab>
               </div>

            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="COUR02">
               <byline resp="#BAZA1"><persName/></byline>

               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>How Tarlton Deceived teh Watch in Fleet Street</title></head>
                  <ab>Tarlton was late to Court and when he approached Fleetstreet he saw the
                     police. He did not know how to pass them and he attempted to go by them very
                     fast, thinking that he would go unexamined. However, the police took this
                     action as an act of him completely disregarding their presence and commanded
                     him (in the Queen's name) to stop. Tarlton acted as if he could not stand, he
                     fell to the ground as if he was drunk and so they let him pass because he was
                     intoxicated. </ab>
               </div>


            </div>

            <div type="jest" xml:id="COUR03">
               <byline resp="#BAZA1"><persName/></byline>

               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>How Tarlton Flouted a Lady in the Court</title></head>
                  <ab>One time, Tarlton was at a banquet at Greenwitch. The Queen was there and had
                     her ladies there too. One of them had a full face of pimples and she also
                     refused to drink wine with the other Ladies. Tarlton saw this (and he knew he
                     was there to entertain), and so he began to make fun of her appearance. The
                     rest of the ladies laughed, however she was embarrassed and left the banquet.
                  </ab>
               </div>
            </div>

            <div type="jest" xml:id="COUR04">
               <byline resp="#BAZA1"><persName/></byline>

               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>Tarlton's Opinion of Oysters</title></head>
                  <ab>Certain Noblemen and Ladies were eating Oysters. One of them saw Tarlton and
                     called for him, asking if he liked Oysters. Tarlton replied, stating no because
                     they are an ungodly, uncharitable, and unprofitable meat. In response they
                     asked Tarlton why he thought that, and Tarlton responded by saying that they
                     are eaten without grace, they are uncharitable because they are inside of a
                     shell, and they are unprofitable because they must swim in wine. </ab>
               </div>
            </div>

            <div type="jest" xml:id="COUR05">
               <byline resp="#BAZA1"><persName/></byline>

               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>Tarlton's Resolution of a Question</title></head>
                  <ab>A Gentleman asked Tarlton what time he thought the Devil to be most active?
                     Tarlton's response was, “When the Pope dies, why?”. The Gentlemen replied by
                     saying that then all of the Devils are active to plague him, because he has
                     done many people wrong who want him to be plagued by the Devil. </ab>
               </div>
            </div>

            <div type="jest" xml:id="COUR06">
               <byline resp="#BEAR1"><persName>Haley Beardsley</persName></byline>

               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>How a Parsonage Fell into Tarlton's Hands</title></head>
                  <ab>The Queen was dining in the Strand at the Lord Treasurers house. The lords
                     were very eager for her to stay all night, but nothing would convince her.
                     Tarlton was in his clown costume, being at the dinner, and hearing the sorrow
                     of the noblemen that she would not stay, he asked the nobles what they would
                     give him to convince her to stay. The lords promised him anything to perform
                     it. He said, 'procure me the Shard parsonage. They arranged for the patent to
                     be drawn up; he put on a parson's gown and a corner cap, and standing upon the
                     stairs where the Queen would descend, he repeated these words: 'A parson or no
                     parson? A parson or no parson?' But after she knew what he meant, she not only
                     stayed all night, but the next day will that he should have possession of a
                     benefice. A madder parson there never was, for he threatened to turn the bell
                     metal into lining for his purse - which he did, the parsonage and all, into
                     ready money</ab>
               </div>
            </div>

            <div type="jest" xml:id="COUR07">
               <byline resp="#BEAR1"><persName>Haley Beardsley</persName></byline>

               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>How Tarlton Proved Two Gentlewomen Dishonest by Their Own
                        Words</title></head>
                  <ab>Tarlton seeing in Greenwich two gentlewomen in the garden together, to make
                     myrth, comes to them and enquires thus: 'Gentlemwomen, which of you two is the
                     more honest?' 'I', says the one, 'I hope without exceptions.' 'And I', quoth
                     the other, 'since we must speak of ourselves.' 'So then,' says Tarlton, 'one of
                     you by your own words is dishonest, one being more honest than the other, else
                     you would answer othersie. But as I found you, so I leave you.'</ab>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="COUR08">
               <byline resp="#BEAR1"><persName>Haley Beardsley</persName></byline>

               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>How Tarlton Answered a Wanton Gentlewoman</title></head>
                  <ab>A Gentlewoman merrily disposed, being crossed by Tarlton and half angry, said
                     'Sirra, a little thing would make me requite you with a cuff.' 'With a cuff,
                     lady,' says Tarlton. 'So would you spell my sorrow forward, but spell my sorrow
                     backward, then cuff me and spare not?' When the gentlemen who were near
                     considered the word, their laughing made the simple-meaning gentlewoman to
                     blush for shame</ab>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="COUR09">
               <byline resp="#BEAR1"><persName>Haley Beardsley</persName></byline>

               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>How Tarlton Dared a Lady</title></head>
                  <ab>At the dinner in the great chamber where Tarlton jested, the ladies were
                     daring one another. Quoth one, 'I have always done things that is honest and
                     honorable.' 'A French crown of that,' says Tarlton. 'Ten pounds of that,' says
                     the lady. 'Done,' says one. 'Done,' says another. Tarlton put a two-pence
                     between his lips, and dared her to take it away with her lips. 'Fie,' says she,
                     'That is immodesty.' 'What, to kiss?' says Tarlton. 'Then immodesty bears a
                     great hand over all. But once in your life say you have been beaten at your own
                     weapon.' 'Well, sir,' says she. 'You may say anything.' 'Then says Tarlton,
                     'remember I say you dare not, and so my wager is good.'</ab>
               </div>
            </div>

            <div type="jest" xml:id="COUR10">
               <byline resp="#BROO1"><persName>Aden Brooks</persName></byline>

               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>HowTarlton landed at Cuckolds Haven</title></head>
                  <ab> One Sunday, Tarlton spent the day at court. With the help of a pair of oars,
                     he left during the night. Tarlton was drinking alcohol and the Watermen were
                     also drunk, for the most part. Finally, they left Greenwich at low tide. The
                     Watermen became afraid of the cables by the Lime-house. It was very dark and
                     late, and Tarlton arrived at Cuckold’s-haven. The Watermen told him they would
                     tell him why they were there the following day. Tarlton wanted to walk to
                     Redriffe. He walked through the dirty bank of water which was up to his knees.
                     When he came back home, he had one of his boys help him take off his boots. His
                     socks were stained a different color because of the dirty water he walked
                     through. One of the men asked him about this the next day. "Tarlton, please
                     tell me as I would like to know, did you go to Cuckold’s-haven?” Tarlton
                     answered: “Yes sir, and I was respectful.” </ab>
               </div>

            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="COUR11">
               <byline resp="#BROO1"><persName>Aden Brooks</persName></byline>

               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>The Fight Between Tarlton and Black Davie</title></head>
                  <ab>Not long ago, lived a boaster named Black Davie who would fence with any
                     gentleman for money. He was hired to draw upon Tarlton, for breaking a jest
                     upon Kate, a “punk” men called her. One evening Tarlton arrived at the court
                     gate at Whitehall. He walked toward the Tilt-yard and Davie immediately drew
                     upon Tarlton, who although he was amazed, fought back. Tarlton couragiously
                     took him in his arms and threw him into the Tilt-yard. Davie fell on his nose,
                     and broke it. Davie spent all night laying in the Tilt-yard, waiting for the
                     doors to open . The Barber surgeons told him what happened, since Tarlton was
                     at a tavern with Cockatrice huffing Kate. Tarlton asked for wine, but she told
                     him that he would burn without it so she would not drink it. He then answered,
                     “how shall I be burned, as you cannot burn without fire?” She then replied,
                     “Marry me, take the cup in your hand and I will tell you.” He filled thecup in
                     her hand and said it was burned sufficiently in a fiery place. She perceived
                     herself in such a way that she hired me to win the fight against herself. </ab>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="COUR12">
               <byline resp="#CALD1"><persName>Julia Calderone</persName></byline>

               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>How Tarlton Answered the Watchmen Coming from the
                     Court</title></head>
                  <ab> Tarlton having played before the Queen, until one o’clock, coming home, one
                     of them spotted him as asked “sir, who is there?”. Tarlton answered by saying
                     “a woman” was there and the Watchmen called him out his lie by reasoning that
                     women do not have beards. Tarlton replies, explaining that if he had said he
                     said a man, which the watchmen know to be true, they would have reasoned
                     otherwise. Therefore, I said woman, and so I am all woman, having pleased the
                     Queen by being a woman. Another watchmen responds by saying “I present the
                     Queen”. Then I am a women indeed, Tarlton says, as well as you, for you also
                     have a beard and truly Mistris Annis, my buske is not done yet, when will yours
                     be done? Leave the lying fellow, said the Watch. The Queen’s order is that
                     whoever is taken without doors after ten o’clock, shall be committed, and now
                     it is past one. Commit all, says Tarlton, for it be past one o’clock, it will
                     not ten this eight hours. One of the watchmen lifts up his lantern, and looks
                     him in the face, and knew him. Indeed Mr. Tarlton you have more wit then we all
                     do, for it is true that ten was before one, but now one is before ten. It is
                     true, said Tarlton, Watchmen don’t have more wit, but for want of sleep they
                     are turned into fools. So, Tarlton stole from them and the watchmen that seemed
                     wise went home to bed. </ab>
               </div>

               <div type="jest" xml:id="COUR13">
                  <byline resp="#CALD1"><persName>Julia Calderone</persName></byline>

                  <div type="modern">
                     <head><title>Tarlton's Answer to a Courtier</title></head>
                     <ab> After being at the Court all night, Tarlton met a great Courtier coming
                        from his Chamber in the morning. The Courtier said “Good morning Master
                        Didimus and Tridimus”. Tarlton being somewhat abashed, not knowing the
                        meaning of his remark, said “Sir, I do not understand you, expound I pray
                        you”. The Courtuer said Didimus and Tridimus is a fool and a knave. You
                        overload me Tarlton replyed, for my back cannot bear both. Therefore you
                        take one, and I will take the other. You take the knave, and I will carry
                        the fool with me. </ab>
                  </div>

               </div>
               <div type="jest" xml:id="COUR14">
                  <byline resp="#CALD1"><persName>Julia Calderone</persName></byline>
                  <div type="modern">
                     <head><title>Tarlton's Quip for a Young Courtier</title></head>
                     <ab> There was a young Gentlemen in the Court, that has first laid with the
                        Mother, and after with the daughter, and having done so, asked Tarlton what
                        is resembled. He said if you should first have eaten the Hen, and after the
                        Chicken. </ab>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="jest" xml:id="COUR15">
                  <byline resp="#DERR1"><persName>Luke Derr</persName></byline>
                  <div type="modern">
                     <head><title>Tarlton's Answer to a Nobleman's Question</title></head>
                     <ab>There was a nobleman that asked Tarlton what he thought of soldiers in time
                        of peace? He says, they are like chimneys in summer.</ab>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="jest" xml:id="COUR16">
                  <byline resp="#DERR1"><persName>Luke Derr</persName></byline>
                  <div type="modern">
                     <head><title>Tarlton's Jest to an Unthrifty Courtier</title></head>
                     <ab>There was a deadbeat Gallant belonging to the Court that had borrowed five
                        pounds from Tarlton, but having lost it at Dice, he sent his man to Tarlton
                        to borrow five pounds more, already owing him five pounds: tell your master,
                        says Tarlton, that if he will send me the token, I will send him the money:
                        someone who deceives me once, god forgive him: If twice, god forgive him:
                        but three times, god forgive him, but not me, because I could not
                        beware.</ab>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="jest" xml:id="COUR17">
                  <byline resp="#DERR1"><persName>Luke Derr</persName></byline>

                  <div type="modern">
                     <head><title>Tarlton Flouted Two Gallants</title></head>
                     <ab>Tarlton being in a bad mood, as he walked in the great hall in Greenwich,
                        he met my old Lord Chamberlain, going between two fantastic gallants, and
                        cryed aloud onto him, my lord, my lord, you go in great danger: amazed, he
                        asked where: if not for those two blades under each of your arms.</ab>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>

         <div type="section" xml:id="CITY">
            <head><title>Tarlton's Sound City Jests</title></head>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="CITY01">
               <byline resp="#DERR1"><persName>Luke Derr</persName></byline>

               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>Tarlton's Jest of a Red Face</title></head>
                  <ab>To an ordinary in the White Friers, where gentlemen used, by reason of
                     extraordinaire diet, to this Tarlton often frequented, as well to continue
                     acquaintance, as to please his appetite: it chanced so upon a time (especially)
                     being set amongst the gentlemen and gallants, they asked him why sadness
                     overtook his happiness, to which he said little, but squinting, he looked for a
                     jest to make them happy; at last he found one on his left side, which had a
                     very red face, he being a very great gentleman he presently in great confidence
                     called his host: who I serve as my host? Tarlton said, the Queen’s Majesty,
                     replied the good man of the house: how is that Tarlton says, to her Majesties
                     disgrace, you dare make me a companion with servingmen, clapping my Lord
                     Shandoyes upon my sleeve, looking at the gentleman with the red face, he says,
                     it sits like the Sarazens head without Newgate: the Getlemans Salamanders face
                     burnt like Aetna for anger, the rest laughed: in the end all enraged, the
                     gentleman swore to fight him at the next meeting. </ab>
               </div>

            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="CITY02">
               <byline resp="#HASF1"><persName>Andrew Hasfal</persName></byline>

               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>A Sudden and Dangerous Fray Between a Gentleman and Tarlton, Which He
                        Put Off with a Jest</title></head>
                  <ab>As Tarlton and others passed along Fleet Street, he saw a dapper young man
                     with long dark hair hanging down over his ears, and an Italian-style cut beard,
                     wearing white satin, very quaintly cut, and the suit so stiffly starched that
                     he could barely bend over. Tarlton is amazed by this man and passed along the
                     wall-side (which is where the upper-classes walk, away from the street),
                     knowing that one so proud-looking would expect that measure of respect. The
                     gallant, insulted that an actor would upstage him like this, drew his sword.
                     Tarlton drew as well. The gentleman started to fight, but Tarlton held his own.
                     and began to mock the man by opening his mouth, causing passersby to laugh. The
                     gallant enquired why he did this. 'O, sir,' says Tarlton, 'in hopes to swallow
                     you, for by my troth you look like a prune in soup.' At this point the crowd
                     broke up the fight, and the gentleman, noting Tarlton's sense of humor, went
                     away because he did not know how to respond. </ab>
               </div>

            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="CITY03">
               <byline resp="#HASF1"><persName>Andrew Hasfal</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>Tarltons Jest of a Pippin</title></head>
                  <ab>At the Bull in Bishopsgate Street, where the Queen’s Players often played,
                     when Tarlton was coming on stage, someone from the gallerie threw a pippin at
                     him. Tarlton took up the pippin and looked at it and came up with this
                     jest:</ab>
                  <ab>'Pip in or nose in, choose one. Put yours in, or else I put in the other.
                     Pippin you have put in, but for my grace would I put your nose in the other
                     place. </ab>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="CITY04">
               <byline resp="#HASF1"><persName>Andrew Hasfal</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>A Jest of an Apple Hitting Tarlton on the Face</title></head>
                  <ab>Tarlton having taunted the gentlemen for the apple he threw, the man wanted to
                     get back at him. In the play Tarlton was supposed to kneel down for his
                     father's blessing. The audience member threw the apple at Tarlton and it hit
                     him on the cheek. Tarlton kneeled down and asked god for a blessong for the man
                     who thre the apple at his cheek. Tarlton grabs the apple and made this jest: </ab>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Gentlemen, this fellow with his face of mapple.</l>
                     <l>Instead of a pippin hath throwne me an apple:</l>
                     <l>But as for an apple he hath cast a crab,</l>
                     <l>So instead of an honest woman God hath sent him a drab.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <ab>The people laughed heartily, because he had a whore for a wife.</ab>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="CITY05">
               <byline resp="#HEIN1"><persName>Rebecca Heintzelman</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>How Tarlton and One in the Gallery Fell Out.</title></head>
                  <ab> It happened in the middle of a play, when the audience was waiting
                     expectantly for Tarlton to appear, he finally came forth. When he entered, one
                     in the gallery pointed his finger at him and, turning to a friend who had never
                     seen Tarlton, explained who it was. Tarlton, who was eager to make a joke at
                     any opportunity, saw the man point with one finger, and he in turn held up two
                     fingers. The captious man, who was married and jealous of his wife, took
                     offense to Tarlton’s action, especially because he was a prominent player. He
                     asked Tarlton why he made horns at him, and Tarlton replied, “No, they are
                     fingers, for there is no man who will show me a finger without me returning the
                     gesture.” “No, no,” says the man, “you gave me the horns.” “True,” says
                     Tarlton, “for my fingers are tipped with nails, which are like horns, and I
                     must make a show of you.” The matter grew so that the more the man meddled, the
                     more he was disgraced. The other bystanders told him to give up and leave
                     before his cause grew more desperate, so the man pulled his hat over his eyes
                     and left. </ab>
               </div>

            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="CITY06">
               <byline resp="#HEIN1"><persName>Rebecca Heintzelman</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>How Fiddlers Fiddled Away Tarlton’s Apparel.</title></head>
                  <ab> It happened that one Fancy and Nancy, a group of musicians in London, would
                     come with their friends to visit Tarlton, who was one of their oldest friends
                     and benefactors. At this time, Tarlton lived at a tavern on Gracious Street
                     called the Saba, and the musicians came by one summer morning to play a song
                     and wake up Tarlton. In recognition of their efforts, Tarlton opened his
                     bedroom door and gave them muscadine. A thief watched this and noticed that
                     Tarlton had left his room in his shirt and nightgown to drink with his friends.
                     The thief stepped into Tarlton’s room and took his clothes, thinking that if he
                     were caught, he would make his actions into a jest, but no one saw him and he
                     went on his way. Shortly afterwards, Tarlton returned to his room and looked
                     for his clothes, but he could not find them. The next day, news of this story
                     was spreading, and someone in the crowd mocked Tarlton while he was performing
                     at the Curtain, saying, </ab>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Tarlton I will tell you a jest,</l>
                     <l>Which after turned to earnest:</l>
                     <l>One there was as I heard say,</l>
                     <l>Who in his shirt heard music play,</l>
                     <l>While all his clothes were stolen away.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <ab>Tarlton smiled and replied by saying,</ab>
                  <lg>
                     <l>That's certain, Sir, it is no lie,</l>
                     <l>That same one in truth was I:</l>
                     <l>When that the thief shall pine and lack,</l>
                     <l>Then shall I have clothes to my back:</l>
                     <l>And I together with my fellows,</l>
                     <l>May see him ride to Tiburne Gallows.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="CITY07">
               <byline resp="#KIZI1"><persName>Jackson Kizilbash</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>Of Tarlton and a Beggar.</title></head>
                  <ab>There was a poor beggar, a conceited fellow, who seeing Tarlton at his door
                     asked him to give him some money. Tarlton, putting his hand in his pocket, gave
                     him two pence instead of a penny. Tarlton then made this rhyme:</ab>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Of all other Beggers most happy thou art,</l>
                     <l>For to thee my hand is better then my heart.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <ab>Answered the Begger.</ab>
                  <lg>
                     <l>True it is Master, as it chanceth now,</l>
                     <l>The better for me, and the worse for you.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="CITY08">
               <byline resp="#KIZI1"><persName>Jackson Kizilbash</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>How Tarlton Deceived a Doctor of Physick</title></head>
                  <ab>Tarlton, to amuse certain gentlemen who were aquaintances of his, went to a
                     simple doctor of physick that lived not far from Islington. He took a large
                     urinal and filled it half full of good wine, and took it to this doctor, saying
                     that it was a sick man's urine. The doctor, shook the urinal as though he had
                     great knowledge. He said, 'the patient this piss is bad, and the patient needs
                     to be purged of blood, and make sure it's ten ounces of blood.' 'No, you
                     dunce,' replied Tarlton, 'it is good piss,' and with that drank it all, and
                     threw the urinal over his head.</ab>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="CITY09">
               <byline resp="#KIZI1"><persName>Jackson Kizilbash</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>How Tarlton Frightened a Country Fellow</title></head>
                  <ab>Tarlton passing through London, by chance heard a simple country fellow in an
                     ale house calling for a Kingstone pot of ale. Tarlton stepped into him and
                     threatened to accuse him of treason, saying 'Sirra, I have seen and tasted a
                     penny pot of ale, and have found the price to be good. But a Kingstone coin I
                     never heard, therefore it must be some counterfeit, and I must know how you
                     came by it.' Hereupon the country fellow was driven into such anxiety that he
                     ran out of doors and took to his heels as though he was being followed by
                     wildfire.</ab>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="CITY10">
               <byline resp="#KIZI1"><persName>Jackson Kizilbash</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>How Tarlton was Deceived by His Wife in London</title></head>
                  <ab>Tarlton being merrily disposed, as he and his wife sat together he said to
                     her, 'Kate, answer me one question without lying, and take this crown of gold,'
                     which she took on condition that if she lost she would give it back to him.
                     Tarlton asked, 'Am I a cuckold or not, Kate?' Whereupon she said nothing, but
                     stood silent, regardless that he urged her to answer many times. Tarlton,
                     seeing that she would not speak, asked for his gold back again. 'Why,' asked
                     she, 'Have I said a lie?' 'No', says Tarlton. 'Why then, goodman fool, I have
                     won the wager!' Tarlton, mad with anger, made this rhyme:</ab>
                  <lg>
                     <l>As women in speech can revile a man,</l>
                     <l>So can they in silence beguile a man.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="CITY11">
               <byline resp="#KRES1"><persName>Megan Kreslinski</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>One Asked Tarlton Which Countryman the Devil Was</title></head>
                  <ab>In Carter Lane there lived a merry cobbler, who being in company with Tarlton
                     asked him chich country the devil was from. Tarlton said, 'A Spaniard, for
                     Spaniards, like the devil, trouble the whole world.'</ab>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="CITY12">
               <byline resp="#KRES1"><persName>Megan Kreslinski</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>A Cheesemonger's Question to Tarlton</title></head>
                  <ab>In the time of scarcity, a simple cheesemonger, hearing Tarlton commended for
                     his quick wit, came unto him and asked why he thought cheese and butter were so
                     expensive. Tarlton answered, 'because wood and coals are so expensive for
                     butter and cheese a man may eat without a fire.</ab>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="CITY13">
               <byline resp="#KRES1"><persName>Megan Kreslinski</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>Tarlton's Answer to a Rich Londoner</title></head>
                  <ab>Tarlton meeting a rich Londoner fell into talking about the Bishop of
                     Peterborough, highly praising his generosity to his servants, his liberality to
                     strangers, his great hospitality and charity to the poor. 'He should,' says the
                     rich man,' for what he has is his but during his life.' 'Why,' said Tarlton,
                     'how many lives have you for your goods?'</ab>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="CITY14">
               <byline resp="#KRES1"><persName>Megan Kreslinski</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>How Tarlton Gave Away His Dinner</title></head>
                  <ab>As Tarlton and his wife sat at dinner, his wife being displeased with him and
                     thinking to cross him, she gave away half of his meet to a poor beggar, saying,
                     'Take this for my other husband's sake.' Whereupon Tarlton took all that was
                     left, and likewise bade the poor fellow to pray for his other wife's soul.
                  </ab>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="CITY15">
               <byline resp="#KRES1"><persName>Megan Kreslinski</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>Tarlton's Answer to a Boy in Rhyme</title></head>
                  <ab>There was a crack rope boy, who meeting Tarlton in a London street sung this
                     rhyme to him:</ab>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Woe worth thee Tarlton,</l>
                     <l>That ever thou wast borne:</l>
                     <l>Thy wife hath made thee cuckold,</l>
                     <l>And thou must wear the horn.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <ab>Tarlton presently answered him in extemporary verse.</ab>
                  <lg>
                     <l>What and if I be (Boy)</l>
                     <l>I am ne'er the worse:</l>
                     <l>She keepes me like a gentleman,</l>
                     <l>With money in my purse.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="CITY16">
               <byline resp="#KURU1"><persName>Viveka Kurup</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>How Tarlton Invited Himself to Dinner at the Lord Mayor's
                        House</title></head>
                  <ab>A jest came in Tarlton's head where to dine, and he thought, 'in all that a
                     man does, let him aim at the best, for sure if I bid myself anywhere this day,
                     it shall be to go to my Lord Mayor's house.' Upon this he went to the Compter
                     and entered his action against the Lord Mayor, who was presently told of it,
                     and sent for him. Tarlton waits until dinner time, and then comes, who was
                     admitted presently. 'Master Tarlton,' says the Lord Mayor, have you entered an
                     action against me in the Poultry Compter?' 'My lord,' says Tarlton, 'have you
                     enterred an action against me in Wood Street Compter?' 'Not I, in truth,' says
                     the Mayor. 'No,' says Tarlton, 'he was a villain that told me so then. But if
                     it be not so, forgive me this fault, my lord, and I will never offend again.'
                     But in the end he begins to swear how he will be revenged on him that mocked
                     him, and flings out in a rage. But the mayor said, 'stay, Master Tarlton, dine
                     with me and no doubt but after dinner you will be better minded.' 'I will try
                     that, my Lord,' says Tarlton, 'and if it alter mine anger, both mine enemy and
                     I will thank you together for this courtesy.'</ab>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="CITY17">
               <byline resp="#KURU1"><persName>Viveka Kurup</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>Tarlton's Jest of a Box on the Ear</title></head>
                  <ab>One that fell out with his friend meets him in the street, and calling him
                     into a corner gave him a box on the ear, and knocked him down, and never told
                     him why he do so. Tarlton watching this raised up the fellow and asked him the
                     reason of their sudden falling out. 'Can you tell sir,' said the fellow, 'for I
                     have no idea why this happened.' 'Well,' said Tarlton, 'the more fool you, for
                     had I such feeling of the cause my wit would remember the injury, but many men
                     are goslings; the more they feel the less they conceive.'</ab>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="CITY18">
               <byline resp="#KURU1"><persName>Viveka Kurup</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>Tarlton's Jest to Two Tailors</title></head>
                  <ab>Tarlton meeting two tailors (friends of his) in the evening, in mirth cries,
                     'Who goes there?' 'A man,' answered a tailor. 'How many is there? One?' said
                     Tarlton 'Two,' said the other tailor.' 'Then you say true,' says Tarlton, 'for
                     two tailors goes to a man.' But before they parted, they foxed Tarlaton at the
                     Castle in Paternoster Row, that Tarlton confessed them two tailors to be honest
                     men. So what they spent in the purse they got in the person. Coming but one by
                     Tarlton's account, they returned two. But Tarlton coming one, returned less by
                     his wit, for that was shrunk in the whetting.</ab>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="CITY19">
               <byline resp="#KYAW1"><persName>Wera Kyaw Kyaw</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>How Tarlton joke around with his wife?</title></head>
                  <ab> Tarlton and his wife keeping an ordinary in Paternoster Row, was bidden out
                     to Supper, and because he was a man noted , she would not go with him in the
                     street, but intreats him to keep one side and she another, which he consented
                     to: but as he went he would cry out to her and say, turn that way wife, and
                     anon on this side wife: so the people flock the more to laugh at them, but his
                     wife more then mad angry , goes back again, and almost forswore his company.
                  </ab>
               </div>

            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="CITY20">
               <byline resp="#KYAW1"><persName>Wera Kyaw Kyaw</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>How Tarlton send to a raker’s (specialized street cleaners) horse to
                        cell [in a prison]). </title></head>
                  <ab> When Tarlton dwelt in Gracious stréet, at a Tavern at the sign of the Saba,
                     he was chosen Scavenger: and often the Ward complained of his slacknes in
                     kéeping the stréets cleaner: so on a time when the Cart came, he asked the
                     Raker, why he did his businesse so slackly . Sir said he, my for came, he asked
                     the Raker, why he did his business so slackly . Sir said he, my fore-horse was
                     in the fault , who being let blood and drencht yesterday, I durst not labor
                     him: sir said Tarlton, your horse shall smart (suffer, feel pain) for it, and
                     so leads him to the Counter (to act in opposition to), which the Raker laugh
                     at, and without his horse did his work with the rest, thinking Tarlton honor
                     was to jest, and would return him his horse again anon: but when that anon
                     came, he was faine to pay all his fées of the prison, as directly as if he
                     himself had béene there: for if Tarlton had committed the master, the business
                     had not gone forward, therefore the horse was in prison for the Master. </ab>
               </div>

            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="CITY21">
               <byline resp="#KYAW1"><persName>Wera Kyaw Kyaw</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>How TArlton made Armin his adopted sonne to succeed him.
                     </title></head>
                  <ab> Tarlton kéeping a Tauerne in Gracious stréet, hee let it to another, who was
                     indebted to Armin's Master, a a Gold smith in Lumbard stréet: yet he himself
                     had a Chamber in the same house. And this Armin being then a wag came often
                     thither to demand his Masters money, which hee sometimes had, and sometimes had
                     not: in the end the man growing poore, told the boy he had no money for his
                     Master, and he must bear with him. The man's name being Charles, Armin made
                     this verse, writing it with chalk on a waine-scot: O world how wilt thou lie,
                     is this Charles the great? that I denie: Indeed Charles the great before, But
                     now Charles the lessee, being poor. Tarlton comming into the roome reading it,
                     and partly acquainted with the boyes humor , coming often thither for his M.
                     money, tooke a piece of chalk, &amp; writ this rime by it. A wag thou art, none
                     can prevent thee, And thy desert shall content thee: Let me be divine, as I am,
                     so in time thou'lt be the same. My adopted sonne therefore be, To enjoy my
                     Clowns suite after me. And sée how it fell out: the Boy reading this, so loud
                     Tarlton after, that regarding him with more respect, vsed to his players, and
                     fell in a league with his humour , and private practise brought him to present
                     playing, and at this hour performs the same, where at the Globe on the
                     Back-side men may sée him. </ab>
               </div>

            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="CITY22">
               <byline resp="#MIYA1"><persName>Tsugu Miyake</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>Tarlton greeting with Bankes's horse.</title></head>
                  <ab>There was a man named Bankes (in the time of Tarlton ) who served the Earl of
                     Essex and had a horse of strange qualities. Being at the Crosse-keyes in
                     Gracious street, Bankes earned money with him (as he was mightily resorted to)
                     Tarlton then (with his fellows) playing at the Bell came into the Crosse-keyes
                     amongst many people to see fashions. Bankes perceiving (to make the people
                     laugh ) says "Signior (to his Horse) go fetch me the greatest fool in this
                     group of people". The Jade comes immediatly, and with his mouth drawes Tarlton
                     forth: Tarlton with merry words said nothing, but " God a mercy Horse". In the
                     end, Tarlton sees the people laugh , and was angry inwardly, said, "Sir, if I
                     have the power to use your horse, I would do more then that." Bankes (to please
                     him) said "I will charge him to do it". Then Tarlton says, "charge him to bring
                     me the most whore-master in this group of people". The horse says something to
                     Bankes. "Signior saies he will bring Mr. Tarlton here the greatest Whoremaster
                     in this group". Instead, Horse leads his master to him. Then, "God a mercy
                     Horse indeed, says Tarlton". The people tried hard to keep peace , but Bankes
                     and Tarlton had like to quarrel about where the horse targets at. Ever after it
                     became a story through London, the God-like mercy horse, to this day.</ab>
               </div>

            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="CITY23">
               <byline resp="#MIYA1"><persName>Tsugu Miyake</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>An excellent Jest of Tarleton suddenly spoken.</title></head>
                  <ab>At the Bull at Bishops-gate, there was a play of <name type="play">Henry the
                        fifth</name> , where the Judge was to take a box on the ear. Because the
                     Judge that should take the blow was absent , Tarlton himself (ever forward to
                     please) took upon him to to play the same Judge, besides his own part of the
                     Clown. Knell, who plays Henry the Fifth, punched Tarlton with a great sound,
                     which made the people laugh because it was Tarlton who plays the Judge.
                     Immediately after the Judge disappears, (in his Clown clothes) comes out, and
                     asks the Actors "What news? O says one, have you been here, you should have
                     seen Price Henry hit the Judge with a terrible punch on the ear. "What man",
                     said Tarlton, "strike a Judge?". "It is true with faith", said the other. "No
                     one is like that ", said Judge, " and it must be terrible to the Judge because
                     the report terrifies me, making me think that the blow remains still on my
                     cheek and it burns again." The people laughed at this enormously, and to this
                     day I have heard this story being praised for the uniqueness. However, it was
                     not rare for Tarlton as he had many similar story of these. I would like to see
                     our Clowns in these days to do the similar things like this, and I bet they
                     cannot do better than Tarlton, even though these clowns think they can do a
                     good job .</ab>
               </div>

            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="CITY24">
               <byline resp="#MUEL1"><persName>Nick Mueller</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>Tarlton's Jest with a Boy in the Street</title></head>
                  <ab>A wag-halter boy met Tarlton in the street and said, 'Master Tarlton, who
                     lives longest?' 'Marry, boy,' says Tarlton, 'he that dies last.' 'And why die
                     men so fast,' said the boy? 'Becausae they want breath,' said Tarlton. 'No
                     rather,' said the boy, 'because their time is come.' 'Then your time has come,'
                     said Tarlton. 'See who comes yonder.' 'Who,' said the boy? 'Marry,' said
                     Tarlton, 'Bull the hangman, or one that would willingly be your hangman.'
                     'Nay,' said Tarlton, 'then you will be hanged by your own confession.' And so
                     they parted.</ab>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="CITY25">
               <byline resp="#MUEL1"><persName>Nick Mueller</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>A Jest of Tarlton Proving Mustard Has Wit</title></head>
                  <ab>Tarlton, keeping a pub in Paternoster Row, and sitting with gentlemen to make
                     them merry and standing before them, would approve mustard to have wit. 'How
                     so,' says one? 'It is like a witty scold meeting another scold, knowing that
                     scold will scold begins to scold first.' 'So,' says he, 'the mustard being
                     licked up and knowing that you will bite it, begins to bite you first.' 'I'll
                     try that,' says a dupe standing nearby. And the mustard so tickled him that his
                     eyes watered. 'How now,' says Tarlton, 'does my jest savor?' 'Aye', says the
                     dupe, 'and bit, too.' 'If you had better wit', says Tarlton, 'you would have
                     bit first.' 'So then conclude with me, that dumb unfeeling mustard has more wit
                     than a talking unfeeling fool as you are.' Some were pleased and some were not,
                     but all Tarlton's care was taken before he talked any jest, because that was
                     always his first objective.</ab>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="CITY26">
               <byline resp="#MUEL1"><persName>Nick Mueller</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>How Tarlton Took Tobacco When it First Arrived in
                     England</title></head>
                  <ab>Tarlton (as other gentlemen used) at the first coming up of tobacco, did take
                     it more for fashion's sake than otherwise. Being in a room, sitting between two
                     men overcome with wine, and they never seeing anything like it, wondered at it,
                     and seeing the vapor come out of Tarlton's nose, cried out, 'Fire, fire!' and
                     threw a cup of wine in Tarlton's face. 'Make no stir,' said Tarlton, 'The fire
                     is quenched. If the sheriffs come it will be a fine, as the custom is.' And
                     drinking that again. 'Fie,' says the other, 'what what a stink it makes. I am
                     almost poisoned.' 'If it offend,' says Tarlton, 'let's everyone take a little
                     of the smell, and so the savor will quickly go.' But tobacco whifs made them
                     leave him to pay all.</ab>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>

         <div type="section" xml:id="COUN">
            <head><title>Tarlton's Pretty Country Jests</title></head>

            <div type="jest" xml:id="COUN01">
               <byline resp="#MURR1"><persName>James Murray</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>Tarlton's Wit Between a Bird and a Woodcock</title></head>
                  <ab>In the city of Gloucester, Master Bid of the chapel met with Tarlton, who
                     joyful to re-greet the other, went to visit his friends. Among the rest, Master
                     Bird of the Queen's Chapel visited Master Woodcock of the college, where
                     meeting, many friendly speeches past, amongst which Mastr Woodcock challenged
                     Master Bird of kin, who mused that he was of his affinity and he never knew it.
                     'Yes,' says Master Woodcock, 'Every woodcock is a bird, therefore it must needs
                     be so.' 'Lord, sir,' says Tarlton, 'you are wide, for though every woodcock is
                     a bird, yet every bird is not a woodcock.' So Master Woodcock like a woodcock
                     bit his lip, and Master Bird was silent.</ab>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="COUN02">
               <byline resp="#MURR1"><persName>James Murray</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>Tarlton's Jest of a Gridiron</title></head>
                  <ab>While the Queen's Players were in Worcester city to get oney, it was his
                     custom often to sing extemporaneously of theams give him. Amongst which they
                     were appointed to play the next day. Now one fellow of the city amongst the
                     rest, that seemed quaint of conceit, to lead other youths with his fine wit,
                     gave out that the next day he would give a theam himself, to prove he was the
                     best. Divers of his friends aquainted with him expected some rare conceit.
                     Well, the next day came, and the young man gave his theam in two lines, which
                     were this:</ab>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Methinks it is a thing Unfit.</l>
                     <l>To see a gridiron turn the spit.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <ab>The people laughed at this, thinking his wit knew no answer thereunto, which
                     angered Tarlton exceedingly, and soon with a smile looked about. When they
                     expected wonders he put it off thus:</ab>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Methinks it is a thing nnfit,</l>
                     <l>To see an ass have any wit.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <ab>The people hooted for joy to see the theam-giver dashed, who like a dog with
                     his tail between his legs left the place. But such commendations Tarlton got
                     that he supped with teh bailiff that night, where the theamer dare not come,
                     although he was sent for, so much he was vexed at that unlooked for
                     answer.</ab>
               </div>

            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="COUN03">
               <byline resp="#YIGA1"><persName>Quinton Nsamba Yiga</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>Tarlton's Answer in Defence of his Flat Nose</title></head>
                  <ab>I remember I was once at a play in the country, whereTarlon was, the play
                     being done, every one so pleased to throwe his theme: amongst all the rest, one
                     was read to this same effect, word by word. Tarlton, I am one of your friends,
                     and not your enemy, please tell me how your nose became flat Had I been present
                     at that time on those banks, I would have laid my short sword over his long
                     shanks.(leg) Tarlton mad at this questions, as it was his property sonner to
                     take such a matter ill then well, very suddently he answered him. Friend or
                     enemy, if you need to know, marke me well With parting dogs and beares, then by
                     the ears, this chance fel: But what of that? Though my nose be flat, my credit
                     to saue, Yet very well, I can by the smell, scent an honest state> man from a
                     knaue.</ab>
               </div>

            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="COUN04">
               <byline resp="#YIGA1"><persName>Quinton Nsamba Yiga</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>Tarlton's Jest of a Bristolman</title></head>
                  <ab> When the Quéenes Players were restrained in Summer, they traualied down to
                     S.lames in his Faire, at Bristowe, where they were worthily entertained both of
                     Londoners, and those Citizens; it happened that a wealthy Citizen, called
                     M.Subanke, one morning secretly married his maid, but not so secret, but it was
                     blown abroad: that morning, Tarlton and others, walking in the Fair to visit
                     his familiar friendsofLondon , and being in company of Bristol men, they did
                     see Sunbancke coming, who had this propertie with his neck, not to stiree it
                     any way, but to turn body and all: it chanced at the Fair end, he stood to piss
                     against a wall: would have looked back to thank him, he suddenly turns his body
                     around and all, in the view of many, and showed all, which embarrased him, that
                     ashamed he took into a Tauerene, protesting that he had rather have spent ten
                     pound: Sure said the vinter, the fault is in your neck, who will no turn
                     without the bodies assistnace, and not in M. Tarlton: call you him M. Tarlton,
                     says M. Sunbancke? I Sir, says the Vinter, he is the Quéens lester: he may be
                     whose lester he will be, but this lest agree not with me at this time. </ab>
               </div>

            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="COUN05">
               <byline resp="#OLDF1"><persName>Morgan Oldfield</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>A Jest Broken of Tarlton by a Country Gentleman</title></head>
                  <ab>In the country where the Queen's Players were welcomed to a gentleman's house,
                     the wagon was being unloaded of the costumes. The wagon driver comes to Tarlton
                     and asks him to speak to the steward about his horses. 'I will,' says he, and
                     coming to the steward, 'Sir,' says Tarlton, 'where shall our horses spend the
                     time?' The man looking at Tarlton asking that question suddenly answered, 'if
                     it please you, or them, let them walk a turn or two. Over there is a fair
                     garden. Let them play a game or two at bowls in the alley.' And the steward
                     then departs to go about his other business. Tarlton commending the sudden wit
                     of the steward, said little. But the steward was not quiet, and told the
                     gentleman above how he had gotten the upper hand of Tarlton with his jest. They
                     then laughed heartily. However a servingman, loving Tarlton, came and told him
                     as much. Tarlton, to add fuel to the fire, and loath to leave it alone, went
                     off and got two of the horses and took them to the garden, and turned them into
                     the bowling alley (which was the gentleman's only pasttime), who with their
                     hooves made havoc. The ladies looking down from a window, seeing horses in the
                     garden alley, called the knight who cried out to Tarlton, 'Fellow - what do you
                     mean by this?' 'Nothing, sir,' says Taralton. 'But two of my horses are at
                     seven up, for a peck of provender, a foolish match I made. Now they are playing
                     at bowls. Run, run, your steward may come after and cry rub, rub!' At which,
                     though they smiled, yet the steward had no thanks for his labor, to set the
                     horses to such an exercise. And they could not blame Tarlton, who did but as he
                     was bidden. But by this jest oats and hay, stable-room and all, was plenty.</ab>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="COUN06">
               <byline resp="#PAPA1"><persName>Lucas Papaleo</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>How Tarlton Made One of His Company Utterly Swore off
                        Drunkenness</title></head>
                  <ab>At Salisbury Tarlton and his fellows were to play before the mayor and his
                     brothers. But one of Tarlton's company, a young man, was so drunk that he could
                     not perform. Tarlton was just as angry as he was drunk. He clapped the man's
                     legs a huge pair of bolts; the fellow dead asleep felt nothing. When all was
                     done, they conveyed him to the jail on a man's back, and entreated the jailor
                     to do God good service and let him lie there till he woke up. While they were
                     about their sport the fellow awoke, and finding himself arrested, and the jail
                     hung around with bolts and shackles, he began to bless himself and thought for
                     sure in his drunkeness he had done some wischief. He called out but none came
                     to him. Then he thought truly that his was a capital crime and that he was a
                     prisoner. By and by comes the keeper, and regretted that one so young should
                     come to such a shameful death through hanging. Anon, another comes and another,
                     all saying the same, which further put the young man in a puzzle. But at last
                     come Tarlton and the others, entreating the keeper that if it wasn't too late
                     could they see their friend before they left. The keeper hesitated, but at
                     length the poor drunken man called out for them. In they came. 'Oh, Tom,' says
                     Tarlton, 'hard was thy behavior in drunkeness to murder this honst man, and our
                     hard luck too, to have it reported that one of our company is to be hanged for
                     it.' 'Oh God, oh God,' says the fellow, 'is my fault so great? Then commend me
                     to all my friends.' Well, to make a long story short, the fellow swore off
                     drunkeness if he could escape; they convinced him that they were cunning enough
                     to help him to escape and they got him out of prison and sent him to London
                     ahead of them. He was not a little glad he was gone. But see how this jest
                     played out; by little and little the fellow left his excessive drinking, and in
                     time altered his desire of being drunk.</ab>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="COUN07">
               <byline resp="#PAPA1"><persName>Lucas Papaleo</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>Tarlton Saved His Head From Being Cut Off</title></head>
                  <ab>Tarlton was one time staying in the country and lodging in a comfortable inn.
                     During that time there was a gentleman dwelling in the same town, somewhat
                     frantic and distraught of his wits. This mad man suddenly rushed into Tarlton's
                     bed chamber with his sword drawn, and finding him there in bed would have slain
                     him, saying, 'Villain, were it not valiantly done to strike off your head at
                     one blow?' Tarlton answered, 'tut sir, that's nothing with your worship to do,
                     you can as easily strike off two heads at one blow as one. Wherefore, if you
                     please, I'll go down and call up another, and so you may strike off both our
                     heads at once.' The mad man believed him, and so let him slip away.</ab>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="COUN08">
               <byline resp="#PURI1"><persName>Livy Puri</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>How Tarlton Escaped Imprisonment</title></head>
                  <ab>While heading home, Tarlton had been domineering very late one night with two
                     of his friends along Cheapside when the men were stopped by Master Constable.
                     Master Constable asked, “who goes there? “Three merry men,” responded Tarlton.
                     “That is not sufficient, what are you?” said master constable. “Why,” says
                     Tarlton,“one of us is an eye maker, and the other a light maker.” “What are you
                     saying? Are you mocking me? The one is an eye maker, the other a light maker,
                     which two properties belong onto god only, commit these blasphemers,” says
                     constable. “No, I ask you Mr Constable be good in your office, I will prove
                     what I have said to be true,” replies Tarlton. “If you can’t,” says the
                     constable, “you shall pass, otherwise you three will all be punished.” “Why?”
                     asks Tarlton, “this fellow is an eye-maker, because he is an eyeglasses maker,
                     and this other a maker of light, because he is a candlemaker, that makes your
                     darkest night as light as your lantern.” Constable, seeing the three men so
                     pleasant , was satisfied . The other Watchmen laughed and Tarlton, with his two
                     companions, went home quietly .</ab>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="COUN09">
               <byline resp="#PURI1"><persName>Livy Puri</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>How Tarlton Deceived a Country Wench</title></head>
                  <ab>The Queen’s men were traveling into the West country to perform, and were
                     staying in a small village nearly ten miles from Bristol. In the village was a
                     pretty brown haired girl, who Tarlton decided to propose to, claiming that he
                     had come all the way from London just to marry her. The simple maid was proud
                     to be beloved by one of the Queen’s men and quickly agreed to marriage. While
                     at the Church, with M.Parson ready to perform his duty as officiator began to
                     say, “I Richard take thée Ioane,” but was interrupted by Tarlton who
                     interjected saying,“ I will go and call my fellowes, and come back to you
                     again.” He hastily left the church, and with his horse ,who was ready and
                     saddled, rode towards Bristol to tell his friends of his success with his
                     wench. </ab>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="COUN10">
               <byline resp="#PURI1"><persName>Livy Puri</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>How Tarlton Went to Kill Crows</title></head>
                  <ab>As Tarlton was going into the fields with his rifle to kill crows, he spotted
                     a Daw sitting in a tree which he intended to shoot when he was approached by a
                     stranger. Tarlton said, “Sir, I see a Daw there, which I will shoot at if she
                     sits.” To which the stranger responded, “If she sits then she is indeed a Daw.”
                     “But,” said Tarlton, “if she doesn’t sit, what is she then?” “Marry,” said the
                     stranger, “also a Daw,” upon which the Daw flew away immediately. Tarlton, then
                     merrily spoke a rime, saying: Whether a Daw sit, or whether a Daw fly, Whether
                     a Daw stand, or whether a Daw lie, Whether a a daw creeke, or whether a daw
                     cry, In what case soeuer a Daw perseuer. A Daw is a Daw, and a Daw shall be
                     yours. </ab>
               </div>

               <!-- MODERNIZE -->
            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="COUN11">
               <byline resp="#PYON1"><persName>Jason Pyon</persName></byline>
               <div type="old">
                  <head><title>How a poore Beggerman ouer-reached Tarlton by his wit.</title></head>
                  <ab>AS Tarlton vpon a day sate at his owne doore, to whom came a poore old man,
                     &amp; begged a penny for the Lords sake, wherupon Tarlton hauing no single
                     money about him, askt the begger what money he had, no more money master but
                     one single penny. Tarlton being merrily disposed, called for this penny, and
                     hauing receiued it, gaue it to his boy to fetch a pot of Ale, whereat▪ the
                     Begger grew blancke, and began to gather vp his wits how to get it againe: the
                     pot of Ale for the Beggers penny being brought, he proferred to drinke to the
                     begger: nay stay awhile Master, quoth the begger, the vse is where I was borne,
                     that he that paies for the drinke, must drinke first: thou saist well quoth
                     Tarlton, goe to, Drinke to me then: Whereupon the Begger tooke the Pot, saying,
                     here Master I drinke to you, (and therewithall dranke off euery droppe) now
                     Maister, if you will pledge me, send for it as I haue done: Tarlton séeing
                     himselfe so ouer-reacht, greatly commended the Beggers wit, and withall in
                     recompence thereof, gaue him a Teastor: with that the Begger said, that he
                     would most truely pray to God for him: no answered Tarlton, I pray thée pray
                     for thy selfe, for I take no vsury for Almes déeds.</ab>
               </div>
               <!-- MODERNIZE -->
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>TITLE-MODERNIZED</title></head>
                  <ab/>
               </div>

            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="COUN12">
               <byline resp="#PYON1"><persName>Jason Pyon</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>Of Tarlton's Pleasant Answer to a Gallant, by the Side of the
                        Highway</title></head>
                  <ab>It was Tarlton's occasion another time to ride into Suffolk, being furnished
                     with a very lean large horse, and by the way a lusty gallant met him, and
                     mockingly asked him what a yard of his horse was worth? 'Marry, sir,' said
                     Tarlton, 'I pray you alight and lift up my horse's tail, and they in that shop
                     will tell you the price of a yard.'</ab>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="COUN13">
               <byline resp="#PYON1"><persName>Jason Pyon</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>How Tarlton Would Have Drowned His Wife</title></head>
                  <ab>Once upon a time, Tarlton and his wife were passengers on a ship and came
                     sailing from Southhampton towards London. A mighty storm arose, and endangered
                     the ship, whereupon the captain thereof charged every man to throw into the sea
                     the heaviest thing he could best spare to lighten the weight of the ship.
                     Tarlton, that had his wife there, offered to throw her overboard, but the
                     company rescued her, and being asked why he meant to do this, Tarlton answered
                     'she is the heaviest thing I have, and I can best spare her.'</ab>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="COUN14">
               <byline resp="#PYON1"><persName>Jason Pyon</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>How Tarlton Made His Will and Testament</title></head>
                  <ab>Of late there was a gentleman living in England, that wheresoever he dined,
                     would of every dish take a bit into his gown sleeve. This gentleman being once
                     at dinner at a gentleman's house in the country, there he used his aforesaid
                     quality, in the company of Master Tarlton, who perceiving it said this to the
                     company: 'My masters, I am now determined before you all, to make my last will
                     and testament; and first, I bequeath my soul to God my creator, and my body to
                     be buried in the sleeve of yonder gentleman's gown.' And with that he stepped
                     to him, and turned up the gown's sleeve, whereout dropped a bird, and there a
                     bird, with choice of much other good cheer. Tarlton continued shaking it,
                     saying 'I meant this sleeve, gentleman - this sleeve I meant.'</ab>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="COUN15">
               <byline resp="#ROBE1"><persName>Jack Roberto</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>How Tarlton called out a Scoundrel</title></head>
                  <ab>Tarlton and the scoundrel of a man were passing through a field together when
                     they saw a crow called out from a tree. "Do you see the crow?" The <persName
                        type="guy">scoundrel</persName> asked Tarlton, "it's calling you a
                     scoundrel". Tarlton answered, "No, he invites your worship as the better man".
                  </ab>
               </div>

            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="COUN16">
               <byline resp="#ROBE1"><persName>Jack Roberto</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>Tarton's Joke of a Rural Woman</title></head>
                  <ab>Tarlton was going to Hogsdon. He was going to a market and ran into a woman
                     from the country falling over and over again on her horse. She claimed that
                        <persName type="guy">God</persName> sent her and referencing God, asked
                     Tarlton if he had ever seen the likes of her before. Talrlton responded "Not in
                     good truth, but once before in London".</ab>
               </div>

            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="COUN17">
               <byline resp="#ROBE1"><persName>Jack Roberto</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>How Tarlton Tricked a Hotel Owner at Sandwich</title></head>
                  <ab>Once upon a time when the players were quieted , Tarlton and his friend
                     journeyed in the Country for so long that they used all their money. They were
                     very far from London, and didn't know what to do. Tarlton gathered his thoughts
                     and and came up with a plan to trick someone into getting him to London with no
                     money. They went to a Hotel in Sandwich and were charged a lot of money for two
                     days, even though they couldn't pay it. On the third morning, he told his
                     friend to go down and to tell the Hotelowners that he serves a Seminary Priest
                     and a Jesuit. The boy kept mumbling on and on about the situation he was in
                     with Tarlton. The hotel owners were sent to the room that Tarlton was staying
                     in. Tarlton set the room up to go along with the story that his friend had told
                     the Hotel workers. The workers looked through the peep-hole in the door and saw
                     the scene that <persName type="guy">Tarlton</persName> had made as a Seminary
                     Preist. They barged into the room and arrested Tarlton for being a Seminary
                     Priest. They brought Tarlton and his friend up to London in hope that they
                     would get rich rewards for turning in the criminals. They presented him to M.
                     Fleetwood, who was a judge in London. When the Judge saw Tarlton, he knew him
                     right away. Tarlton courteously entertaiend the judge which enraged and hotel
                     owners as they had no idea what was going on. They walked away in shame and in
                     anger for the troubles they were put through. Tarlton tuanted and laughed at
                     them as they walked away as he had outwitted them. </ab>
               </div>

            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="COUN18">
               <byline resp="#SCHA1"><persName>Katie Schaefer</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>Of Tarlton's Wrongful Accusation</title></head>
                  <ab>Once upon a time, Tarlton was wrongfully accused of getting a gentleman's maid
                     with child, and for that reason was brought before a justice in Kent. That
                     justice said as follows, 'It is a marvel, Master Tarlton, that you - being a
                     gentleman of good quality, and one of her Majesty's servants, would venture
                     thus to get a maid with child.' 'Nay, rather,' said Tarlton, 'it would be a
                     marvel if a maid had gotten me with child.'</ab>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="COUN19">
               <byline resp="#SCHA1"><persName>Katie Schaefer</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>Tarlton Deceived by a Country Wench</title></head>
                  <ab>Tarlton traveling to play abroad, was in a town where, in the inn, was a
                     pretty maid whose favor was placed in a corner of Tarlton's affection. And
                     talking with her, she appointed to meet with him at the bottom of a pair of
                     stairs. The night and the hour arrived, and the maid subtly sent down her
                     mistress, whom Tarlton caught in his arm. 'Art come, wench,' says he? 'Out,
                     alas,' says the mistress, not knowing who it was. Tarlton, hearing it was the
                     mistress, started aside and the maid came down with a candle, and she caught a
                     glimpse of Tarlton in the dark, who stepped into another room. 'How now,
                     mistress,' said the maid. 'Something,' said she, 'frightened me. Some man, for
                     sure I heard him speak.' 'No, no, mistress,' said the maid, 'it is no man. It
                     was a bull calf that I shut into a room till John, our pounder, came to have
                     pounded him for a stray.' 'Had I thought that,' said she, 'I would have hit him
                     such a knock on his forehead that his home should never have graced his
                     forelock.' And so she departs again, afraid. But how did Tarlton took this
                     jest, think you?</ab>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="COUN20">
               <byline resp="#SCHA1"><persName>Katie Schaefer</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>How Tarlton Could Not Abide a Cat, and Deceived
                     Himself</title></head>
                  <ab>In the country, Tarlton told his hostess that he was a conjurer. 'Oh sir,'
                     says she, 'I had pewter stolen off my shelf the other day. Help me to find it,
                     and I won't charge you for all the pots of ale you owe me - which is sixteen
                     dozen.' Tarlton says, 'Tomorrow morning the devil shall help you to find it, or
                     I will trounce him.' Morning came, and the hostess and Tarlton met in a room by
                     themselves. Tarlton, to pass the time with exercising his wit, pretended to
                     conjure the devil, when truthfully he had no more skill than a dog. But see the
                     just, how contrarily it came to pass: as he was calling out 'Mons, pons, simul,
                     and sons' and such like, a cat unexpectedly leapt from the gutter window. The
                     sight so amazed Tarlton that he skipped out and threw his mistress to the
                     ground. He departed with his fellows, and left her hip out of joint. But being
                     in a doctor's care, she dared not tell how it happened.</ab>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="COUN21">
               <byline resp="#SCHM1"><persName>Caleb Schmidt</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>How Tarlton and the Hostess of Waltham met</title></head>
                  <ab>Tarlton rode along with friends, and citizens to make merry to Waltham. On the
                     way he met his hostess while riding toward London, to which some of his old
                     acquaintances were saluted. The Hostess where Tarlton was going. Tarlton told
                     her to come to Waltham, and requested company Christopher Marlowe’s house.
                     Tarlton do not go and spend your money, not unless we go back to the hound. She
                     lost their customs, and was sent back to London by her man who was sent to go
                     back with them. She was an exceeding and very honest woman, and would do
                     anything, which Tarlton heard as wise as she was, thinking of her mind. He was
                     deceived, yet he asked her if the biggest bed in her house was able to fit
                     them. Meaning himself and her, yes she says and tumble up down at pleasure. Yea
                     one under another says Tarlton, under she says. She agreed to everything like a
                     subtil hostess, and it fell out so that Tarlton, having her in a room in her
                     house, asked her which of those two beds were big enough for them two. This
                     being said she therefore went to be, sweetheart come to thee. Masse says
                     Tarlton my boots were off, I would indeed. I will help you sir , if you please.
                     Yeah, thought Tarlton is the wind in that door? Come on, then. And she very
                     diligently began to pull, til one boot was half off. Now says she, this being
                     hard to be done, let me try cunning on the other and so get both off. But,
                     having both off his legs she left him at the shoemakers. She then went to
                     london where Tarlton was three hours way, and he had no help. But being eased
                     off his pain, he made this rhyme for a theme. Singing it all the way to London.
                     Women are wanton, and hold it no sinne, By tricks and devices to pull a man in. </ab>
                  <ab>Tarlton rode with a group of friends, and citizens to go to Waltham, courtesy
                     of his Hostess while riding toward London.</ab>
               </div>

            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="COUN22">
               <byline resp="#SIMS1"><persName>Sullivan Sims</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>Tarlton's Meeting With His Country Acquaintance at
                     Ilford</title></head>
                  <ab>On Sunday, Tarlton rode to Ilford where his father kept; and dining with them
                     at his sisters, there came in diverse country men to see him, amongst who was
                     one plain country farmer, who said he was Tarlton’s relative who called himself
                     his cousin. But Tarlton demanded the truth from his father if it was true. But
                     he knew no such matter. Whereupon Tarlton says whether he is my relative or not
                     we will be cousins until we part, if we drink in Ilford to do so. So they
                     freely made their way into line so that in briefe they were soundly. Night came
                     and Tarlton would not let his cousin go. But they lied together that night
                     meaning to drink their departure the next morning. Tarlton would by wit leave
                     him in the lash, since power would not. But see the jest. That night, plaine
                     fellow and tarlton in his bed, he had been thinking about the church wall, For
                     we were crying for a fresh shirt. So when he was better they must drink at
                     parting. Indeed to seal the kinfried soundly the fellow had his loade; for,
                     hearing that his cousin Tarlton was gone to london. Angry, he would follow, no
                     one would hold him back. He would go to london, but his aim was so good he went
                     to Rumford to sell his hogs.</ab>
               </div>

            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="COUN23">
               <byline resp="#SIMS1"><persName>Sullivan Sims</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>Tarlton's Answer to a Question</title></head>
                  <ab>Someone asked Tarlton why Monday was called Sunday's friend! Because he is a
                     friend, Tarlton says, to compare with that of the holy day. But it may be that
                     Monday thinks of himself as Sunday's friend, because he follows Sunday, and is
                     the next day after:But he comes a day after the fare for that. Never, says the
                     fellow, but if two Sundays fall together, Monday then may be the first, and it
                     would shew well too. Yes, says Tarlton, But if my nose stood under my mouth it
                     would be better and more profitable. Hoe for my gaim said the fellow? Matty
                     said Tarlton never is cold in the winter, being too close to every dog's tail.
                     The fellow seeing a foolish question had a foolish answer, laid his legges on
                     his neck, and got him gone</ab>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="COUN24">
               <byline resp="#SOTI1"><persName>Harrison Sotir</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>Tarlton's Desire of Enough for Money</title></head>
                  <ab>Tarlton was coming into the market town and bought oats for his horse and what
                     the biggest amount with the money he had. The man said you can sir and gave him
                     8 dry quarts. Tartlon thought his horse should eat well that night and comes to
                     him with the food. Jack Nag was speaking on the behalf of someone and said he
                     was healthy and he faces danger . I have enough money and said you should have
                     it. However when Jack Nag smelt them they were off and said he did not want
                     any. Thank you master : which seeing this Tarlton runs into the market and
                     slashed and cut . But then the next day the man was not able to be found and
                     Tarlton must have escaped. </ab>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="COUN25">
               <byline resp="#SOTI1"><persName>Harrison Sotir</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>How Tarlton's Dog Licked up Six-Pence</title></head>
                  <ab>Tarlton in travels had a dog with really good qualities amongst the good
                     things that he does he always would carry money at the end of his tongue which
                     he would often brag about and tell people. Never was like that. Yes said a lady
                     mine is more strange for he will have the french crown in this mouth. No says
                     Tarlton i think not. Lend me a French crowne says the lady and you shall see
                     me. Truly, madame, I don’t have it, but your dog will carry a cracked >English
                     crowne, here it is. But the lady perceived not the jest but was desirous to see
                     the dogs tricks of 6 pence. Tarlton threw down a teaster and said ‘Bring Sirra’
                     and luckily the dog took up a counter and let the money lie. A woman after
                     seeing that asked him how long he would hold it! ‘ An hour ,’ said Tarlton.
                     ‘That is pretty,’ said the woman, ‘let’s see that.’ In the meantime she picked
                     up the sixe-pence and willed him to let them see money again; when he did see
                     money it was a counter and he made this time. Alas, alas how come all this to
                     pass! The world's worse than it was; for silver turns to brass . I say the lady
                     and the dog has mad his master an ass. But Tarlton would never trust his dogs
                     to do more tricks. </ab>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="COUN26">
               <byline resp="#WARD1"><persName>Lily Ward</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>Tarton's Jest of a Horse and a Man</title></head>
                  <ab>In the city of Norwich, Tarlton was invited to hunt. There was a godly
                     gentlewoman, that bravely mounted on a black horse, rode exceedingly well, to
                     the wonder of all the people; and no one stood in her way. But, Pegasus, her
                     horse, was swift and flew over all. Everyone went home and at dinner everyone
                     comended his pester and his wild disposition and she above all her horse. And,
                     she said, I love no creature so much, at this moment, my gallant horse. Yes,
                     lady, a man better, says Tarlton. Indeed no, she said, not now, since my last
                     husband died I hate them the most, unless you can give me medicines to make me
                     love them. Tarlton made this jest instant. Why, a horse goes that way, madam, a
                     man mimics amber. A horse is for your way madam, but a <persName>man</persName>
                     for your chamber. Lord have mercy, Tarlton, said the men: which gentlewoman is
                     noting, seeing they took exceptions at her words, to make all well, answered
                     this: That a horse is my opinion now, I deny not, And when a man does more good
                     in my chamber I do not defy him. But until then give me room to love something.
                     Then I will please you, said Tarlton. I am glad of that, therefore I pray God
                     send you a good thing or none at all. </ab>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="COUN27">
               <byline resp="#WARD1"><persName>Lily Ward</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>Tarlton's Talk with a Pretty Woman</title></head>
                  <ab>Gentlewoman, said Tarlton, and the rest as you sit, I can tell you strange
                     things: how many people at dinner noted one woman who was being little and
                     pretty . But her prettiness had a wide mouth, which she tried to hide. She
                     would pinch her speech, and speak small, but had a desire to hear news. Tarlton
                     told that his travelling from London to Norwich, was a proclamation that was
                     made that every man should have two wives. Now Jesus questioned her, is it
                     possible? Gentelwoman and otherwise able to or contrarily woman have a large
                     superrority, for every woman must have three husbands. Now Jesus, said the
                     gentlewoman and with wonder skews the full wideness of her mouth, which all the
                     table smiled at, which she realized would answer no more. Now miss, said
                     Tarlton, your mouth is less than it ever was, for now you are able to say
                     nothing. Now arent you a dishonest man, she said. Miss and that is something,
                     yet, said Tarlton, your mouth shall be as wide as it ever was for that jest.
                  </ab>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="COUN28">
               <byline resp="#ZELI1"><persName>Tim Zelikovsky</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>A Jest of Tarlton to a Great Man</title></head>
                  <ab>There was a great fat man, three yards around in the waist, at St Edmondsbury
                     in Suffolk, that died recently. His name was M. Blague, and a good, kind
                     justice, too, and caring for the poor. This justice met with Tarlton in
                     Norwich. 'Tarlton,' said he, 'give me your hand.' 'But you, sir, being richer,
                     may give me a greater gift - give me your body.' And embracing him, Tarlton
                     could not wrap his arms around his waist. Being merry in talk, the justice
                     said, Tarlton, tell me one thing. What is the difference between a flea and a
                     lous?' 'Marry, sir,' said Tarlton, 'as much and like difference as between you
                     and me. I, like a flea, see else, can skip nimbly, but you, like a fat louse,
                     creep slowly, and you can go no faster, though butchers are ready to catch you
                     and hit you on the head.' 'You are a knave,' said the justice. 'Aye, sire, I
                     knew that, before I came here, otherwise I would not be here now, for if one is
                     a knave, one seeks out another.' The justice, understanding him, laughed
                     heartily.</ab>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="COUN29">
               <byline resp="#ZELI1"><persName>Tim Zelikovsky</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>Tarlton's Jest to a Maid in the Dark</title></head>
                  <ab>Tarlton, walking in the dark was groping his way around. He heard the tread of
                     some one approaching him. 'Who goes there?' says he, 'a mon or a monster?' Said
                     the maid, 'a monster.' Said Tarlton, 'Give me a candle', to see who it was.
                     'Indeed,' said he, 'a monster I'll be sworn, for your teeth are longer than
                     your beard.' 'Oh sir,' said the maid, 'speak only of what you see, for women
                     cannot be recognized these days.'</ab>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="jest" xml:id="COUN30">
               <byline resp="#ZELI1"><persName>Tim Zelikovsky</persName></byline>
               <div type="modern">
                  <head><title>Tarlton's Jest to a Dog</title></head>
                  <ab>Tarlton and his friends were drinking in the Bishop of Worcester's wine
                     cellar. Having drunk too much, Tarlton got up and went for a walk through the
                     streets. A dog, sleeping on a dunghill, saw Tarlton stagger toward him, and
                     barked. 'How now, dog,' says Tarlton, 'are you in your humors?' And for a long
                     while afterwards, the phrase for a man being drunk was that he was in his
                     humors.</ab>
               </div>

            </div>
         </div>

      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
